software engineering radio episode 84
the Abrial unless
[Music]
so listeners welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio this is
another episode we are recording at
Uppsala 2007 and actually we were
talking to the Gabriel who is the chair
of Upsala 2007 so welcome dick to the
show glad to be here thank you and first
of all thanks for organizing this
conference I found it really nice so
thanks for all the work you've put in
yeah it's a lot more work than the
general chair is led to believe at the
beginning I've been working on it for
128 weeks
Wow sounds really like a lot of work so
you were also the person who made these
rooms available to us so thanks again
for that okay good yeah absolutely so
why don't you introduce yourself to our
listeners a little bit so my name is
dick Gabriel my background is some
degrees in mathematics then artificial
intelligence at Stanford University I
worked with the John McCarthy at
Stanford for a few years I started my
own company after that it was a lisp
company called lucid and it existed from
1984 to 1994 after that I went to park
place systems where I did more
management stuff by sort of accident I
originally went there to write a book
with Adelle Goldberg and then they had
some development issues and sort of to
see whether the reason that I felt that
I was fairly effective at lucid was that
I was people the person who hired
everyone I wanted to see whether that
was true or false so I helped them out
then after that I went back to school
and got an MFA in poetry all right I
will talk about that later of it and
then since then I've been at Sun
Microsystems and now IBM Research okay
cool
so y'all already mentioned the topic we
are going to focus mainly about on in
this in this episode that is less yeah
so why don't you give us a little
introduction Lisp in three minutes what
is it all about
so Lois pairs a couple it's one of the
couple interesting features one of the
earliest languages it was developed this
is its 49th birthday this year
it's a the core of Lisp is a functional
language which means that everything in
the language is a function which means
it takes arguments and returns a value
and then the way computation is done is
by nesting functions so you call a
function with some arguments it returns
a value and that value is the argument
to other function calls etc etc it's
interesting because the data structure
the primary data structure but not the
only one the list is also the data
structure that encodes the program's
right and so programs and data are the
same so you can construct list programs
using list programs and execute them at
the same time and that was thought to be
how artificial intelligence would work
you'd have a program that was
artificially smart it would construct
programs on the fly and execute them
thereby learn or be told things since
then that's from the early 1960s since
then it's developed into a full-fledged
kind of a systems programming language
so it was an early sort of header
limitations of threads and threads
there's a built in compilers within the
runtime memory managers operating system
interfaces so typically list programmers
feel like they live inside of the
language and live inside a running
execution of it much as a small talk
right oh yeah yeah so in addition to
having lisps lists and functions as the
main abstractions other aspects that are
important probably a side-effect
freeness right as for the for the
functional core yes but for the
non-functional core it's an imperative
language so you do have sensing so you
can do things so there's a function
called probe which stands for program
and what the function does is it takes
no arguments and then what it does is it
executes it defines some local variables
it then executes a sequence of
instructor sequence of functions one
after the other all of which probably
have some sort of side effect and then
it returns the value of the last
and you can put labels in there and go
twos and stuff like that so called the
program feature mm-hmm
there is an assignment operator now lisp
is very famous for not using obvious
names of things so yes the assignment
operator is called set cue so set quote
the reason that it's set cue set quote
is that because it's a fundamentally a
functional language everything is
evaluated so you need something that
says don't evaluate this L so in Lisp if
the Lisp interpreter sees a list it
interprets that as a function call where
the first thing is the function
everything else is an argument if you
want that thing to be treated as a list
you have to quote on it okay so there
are side effects there are object or
extensions there are arrays and complex
numbers and you name it it's got hash
tables on and on so you already already
mentioned that Lisp has come out of the
AI community can you talk a little bit
about the mindset of how things were
back then why Lisp
became the way it was in addition to
just being able to construct itself
what was the the 'quran goal what was
the context so the Graham goal and this
is probably more my opinion than the
accepted opinion was that the artificial
intelligence people were endeavoring to
write programs that no one knew how to
write and so it was the the idea that
you could sort of sit down and say well
you know here is my problem here are the
requirements let me come up with a
specification and now code that up
completely crazy as far as the AI people
are concerned you know they want to sit
down and write a program that
demonstrates some version of human
intelligence by human behavior yeah
there's no idea and so the only way to
do it was to experiment well let me try
this let me add that let me try to add
this fuzzy concept let me try to add
scheduling let me add agendas let me add
resources let me have the resource
limitations and so the idea is you're
always you're constructing a system that
you hope one day we'll show some
intelligence but you're not constructing
it like making a ton of source code and
compiling it periodically you can
you the way you construct a city you
build some of it it's running all of the
time so it's kind of like a live
programming language I think that's
because the tasks over the the the work
of writing artificial intelligence
programs is considered too far away from
what people know how to do mm-hm
so let's look a little bit more closely
at some of the interesting features and
one thing that I'm particularly
interested in is this thing there's
programs as data and data as programs so
that was basically the first
implementation of meta programming yes
so can you talk a little bit about how
this thing works how do you how do you
do this how do you write well how do you
make a list to become a program there
are several ways the salt I'll tell you
the classical way and the other ways are
refinements to make it work faster
mm-hm so one of the things John McCarthy
was the guy who was sort of responsible
for Lisp he had the original ideas and
he had a team of some grad students I
think six grad students and a couple
other folks who were implementing it
back in the early nineteen sorry the
late 1950s early 1960s at MIT in
Cambridge Massachusetts and at that time
there was sort of a debate among
logicians and mathematicians and
computer scientists but they weren't
called computer scientists then as to
compute ability so at that time people
were talking about touring machines the
von Neumann architecture and and one of
the concerns was Universal computation
was there a function was there some
mechanism that could compute anything
that could be computed yeah so the
touring machine was considered that now
he was considered that but with the
program that the Turing machine ran
which was the universal Turing machine
which would take description of any
other Turing machine and executed that
was a big complicated piece of code
basically yeah so what John McCarthy did
was he said well using list structure
and this functional kind of idea the
universal machine for Lisp is quite
short in fact it fits on about 15 lines
of code and it relies on the fact that
it's interpreting list structure
so when it sees a list it looks at the
first thing if it looks like it's a
function it applies it otherwise it uses
rule so if it's a conditional it does
the logic of that it was a very short
piece of code and one day Steve Russell
said well you know if I took that piece
of code and I hand compiled it then that
could be an interpreter for Lisp mm-hmm
and so he did that and that surprised
John McCarthy and they instill overnight
they had a running implementation of
Lisp when he thought it was going to be
a many many many months took one night
to implement this interpreter and so
when they saw that they realized that
they could use this Universal machine
which they called eval right which is to
evaluate a piece of list structure or
anything that was pass as a program you
could then construct any list you want
and then hand that as an argument to
eval and then that would execute it okay
and so that was the beginning of it and
it just really surprised people that
they could do that so easily mm-hmm so
that's also this notion of the
meta-circular interpreter which is I
think a really great geeky word so it's
it's basically a program that shouldn't
say interprets itself but the
interpreters written with the same tools
and languages as the thing it interprets
right took a lot of people a long time
to understand the the concept of
meta-circular interpreter as kind of
first introduced to first explained by
brian Cantwell Smith in the I think mid
to late 1970s so I mentioned that this
Universal function eval is written in
Lisp
yep and so what Steve Russell did was he
hand compiled it right so you'd think
well okay so eval is written in Lisp so
that means that when eval is executing
it's actually executing itself okay so
there's this concept of you have a base
level program which is what eval is is
interpreting and then eval is what up
one level and it sort of looks at the
list structure and interprets it right
now eval is an ellipse you can imagine
that it's at another base level and that
there's another copy of eval
yeah and it's like that all the way to
the top yeah so that's the meta part
mm-hmm it's circular in that the
language that's implemented in is that
language it's interpreting and the trick
though is at the top you don't go all
the way up forever at the top you need
something like what Steve Russell did
which is a compiled version of it yeah
and so what that is is it's a process
that's exactly like what eval does but
it is an eval itself it's in something
that the physical world can interpret
yeah a C program B Pro via C program it
could be machine language for now one of
the tricks that people use and you can
confuse people who's extremely smart
with this is the way that a lot of
interpreters are actually written is
they write a lisp compiler and then they
write the classical eval which is like a
page or so of code and then you compile
it so consider the definition of a car
so remember Mary said that Lisp uses
interesting names for things so if you
have a list the first element is you can
access it with the list function whose
name is car so if I have the list 1 2 3
then car of that list car of 1 2 3 is 1
yeah so and that has to do is the
contents of the address register there's
the original machine and cooter means
what's give me the rest of the list and
that's contents of the decrement
register so is using ready - all right
well CDR sedi oh yeah and then if you
were going so that gives you the rest of
the list it strips off the first element
if you want to strip off the second
element see DDR pass it on a strip off
the c3 first or a CD so you know any
number of these so you can sit in front
of a lisp system and type in what's
called s-expressions these lists that
are interpreters code you can type them
in and they get eval evaluated right
away yep
so you can type in car of quote 1 2 3
the list 1 2 3 and it works so that
means the function car has a definition
means someone wrote the code for ya
so the definition that is actually used
is defined so de fun is how you decide
apart
function2 fun car it's name of the
function then you say it takes one
argument X yeah and then it's definition
is car of X and you go but wait how can
that work because it's recursive yeah so
you're defining the function car and how
do you do car you call car so if you
keep on doing that it's gonna loop
forever however what happens is the
compiler sees this definition it open
codes that is to say it emits machine
instructions when it sees car it doesn't
care that the name of the function is
compiling his car and so when you define
the compiler you define a few things
like car how that compiles out or how
conditionals etc etc and so these these
sort of meta-circular looking
definitions look ridiculous because they
all look like they're infinite recursive
they're resolved by the compiler and the
resolved by the compiler which sort of
bottoms out this you're taught I out
this tower of Medicine Galera T mmm-hmm
one thing that is always well that some
people consider a criticism of Lisp
others say that's really its essence is
that it basically has no syntax I mean
you have it more or more or less
literally right the syntax tree and form
of Lists right so that also makes it
possible that a user-defined function
looks exactly the same as a built-in
stuff yes which gets to this concept of
growing a language that guy still had in
one of his famous talks that's online on
google video will be put a link to
listen to that yeah we could put a link
to it in the show notes good so can you
talk a little bit about the idea of
growing a language and how that plays
into Lisp yeah so that was another
extraordinarily important thing which I
believe was an accident
in that as you mentioned any function
that is in Lisp the syntax for using it
is identical to is if a user did it now
a person and then they you needed some
special other forms as well so
conditionals so the way that Lisp
interpretation normally works is you get
a list it looks at the first thing it
says I it's a function and then it
evaluates its arguments then it passes
those things as arguments to the
function that would is the first one
right so now if you have a conditional
so you say you know left paren
if you know then some predicates and
then if it's true and if it's false two
separate things right we can't do that
that way because that would say okay I
got if so I evaluate all three things
the predicate the true part in the false
part but I mean you didn't want to do
the false part right you can so you
needed some sort of special form so in
Lisp there are special forms that are
interpreted specially and users can
define those using macros right and so
what this meant is again this endeavor
of trying to write programs that people
can't write artificially intelligent
programs one idea that quickly came to
the floor was Lisp is the wrong language
for writing that program I need a
special program to play chess I need a
special program to understand mushrooms
if you wanted a system to classify I
need a special programming language to
you know understand surfaces and so many
AI researchers would start their
research in in some area trying to make
a program to smart their by defining the
language first that they could express
their concepts in and so they would
immediately extend Lisp so that it would
be easier to write the programs and so a
lot of artificial intelligence research
in the 1960s 70s and early 80's was
figure out roughly what you wanted to do
design the language for it implemented
in Lisp which means that it's an
extension to Lisp so it's just defining
functions and these special forms F and
then write your great program but then
people would invent these great
languages as grad students and their
advisers would say well that was a lot
of work and that language you devised
was really interesting why don't you
write that up as your dissertation and
so people would write you know would
start in some AI project for their PhD
and they would end up publishing a
language definition instead and and the
funny thing was that well today you
would say maybe that isn't really a
different language it's basically call
it a framework because of different
functions and procedures so it's a bit
different from
what people today consider language and
ESL development there is no notion of
adapting the syntax because everything
looks like tweets right and so the other
nice thing is when you're a normal it's
a language designer you have to worry
about the syntax and though there's
tools to make it really easily used to
have to worry about parsing I don't have
to worry about parsing mm-hmm so Lisp
has this uniform thing you know the
first thing is either a special form or
more function and a BOTS absolute you
know 15 lines of code so you don't have
to worry about that you just worry about
the expressiveness of what you're
writing of this stuff yeah I mean if I
were a critic or a cynic I would say you
could do this with XML today and
everybody would say oh that's ugly you
kind of use you know because it's
basically literally a tree so I'm that
limited set of primitives and doing
everything the same way is very elegant
right but it's not necessarily user
friendly if you consider a user to be
some non programmer which is what these
else tend to be focusing on yeah that's
largely true XML you XML to me maybe I'm
naive about it but it wasn't a serious
suggestion right it was but XML to me is
is verbose and so you would have you
know some left angle brackets and some
complicated thing right angle breakfast
and blah blah blah and another set of
angle brackets those angle brackets are
really just left paren and right paren
that's the Nord compact there are some
system so for example the the text
editor Emacs is a very simple engine and
all of all of the commands that you do
that users use our X's are written in a
lisp dialect of Lisp and if they're not
naive users who are using Emacs but
they're not
AI people they're not list programmers
and so it's a very compact language so
you can't and so people less expert at
programming and list and you would think
have probably acted normal people
no--don't domain experts well I agree
with all of that the only other thing
that's about Lisp is Lisp has a type
system some people think oh a lisp is
not
typed language and it I guess is there's
some controversy about the terminology
so what I learned in school was that the
term strongly typed meant that no
operation would be permitted to be
carried out on arguments of the wrong
type site so that's usually interpreted
as the compiler won't produce code for
that right unless that's interpreted as
when you try to do that at runtime it
throws an exception what you're getting
at is that there is a difference between
strong and weak typing and studying and
dynamic observing so weak
Lisp is a strongly typed dynamically
typed strongly that is right so what
that means and and this is useful for
beginners I think because beginners use
would use basic they would use logo they
would use a bunch of other small
language like that is their programs are
not verbose because it's telling the
compiler about types everywhere the
types sort of our done at runtime and so
you know how do you you know how do you
make X the variable X refer to a
floating-point number
well you don't declare that X is a you
know who's gonna hold it and then you
type in the thing you just say set Q X -
you know 3.1415 bla bla bla yeah and
then if you you can ask at runtime what
is the type off you know what X refers
to it says was a floating-point number
yeah
so that makes it a little more compact
which maybe might make it easier for end
users but again I wouldn't bear I
wouldn't say you know let's try it on
them I mean someone has right on yeah
but that's not an argument make can you
briefly explain what macros are we
already mentioned it on while explaining
some meta stuff so in most languages so
for your listeners if you think of
macros it's a string type of operation
so you see some sort of pattern of
string in front of you the compiler does
and says oh this is a macro and it does
a string substitution to what the macro
means so in Lisp it's like that only
different so what the interpreter does
and so the compiler mimics the semantics
of the interpreter suppose you define
the macro
Satish and so I and Satish is going to
be a complicated control construct
that's going to spawn a bunch of
processes and monitor them in a
particular way and provide locks and on
a complicated thing yeah so you can
right left Forenza teshon and some
complicated stuff so you define that as
a macro you say def macro is attached
and then you write a description sort of
a pattern of what the different
components of this expression is going
to look like and then what it does is it
then you write Lisp code that produces
the expression that you want and so the
interpreter and the compiler then when
it sees and as the Tesh expression it'll
run this code that you wrote that will
return as its value a piece of list
structure and then either the
interpreter will use that in place of
this attached expression or the compiler
will compile write result
yeah and so what that means is you
always have sort of syntactically
meaningful units in your macro so you
don't have to worry that you left off a
bracket or a comma or something like
that you're always gonna produce
something that is at least a list
okay so just different from C's
preprocessor anything that's right you
can have it in anything in fact would
sees preprocessor I believe you can you
can define the I don't know C so else
you could tell me if it's wrong or your
listeners can laugh their heads off
I believe you can have the the name of
the the procedure or the function that
is returned be constructed from text
from multiple files so you can't even
easily figure out what the name of the
thing is going to be I don't know I
don't know that yet so you can't do that
with with Lisp so you have this sort of
syntactically easy to get right form and
it's through macros primarily that
people define these sort of domain
specific types so you mentioned in the
beginning that Lisp is at its core
primarily functional language we also
said that it has object-oriented notions
in it there is specifically the C loss
or class I don't know actually how you
the Communist Lisp object system so can
you talk a little bit about how people
got from list to classless and what the
differences are and maybe what flavor of
how oh it has yep so there's a long
history to this one of the important
early meetings that were for object
people was I believe it was in either
1971 or 1972
maybe 73 Alan Kay visited the MIT AI lab
and they talked to each other and they
both learned a lot Alan Kay was always
kind of a lisp fan I believe in the
1960s and they exchanged a lot of ideas
so at that time the the so MIT was a
hotbed of Lisp implementation so they
got kind of interested in it so Carl
Hewitt developed the actor language
which is a little bit different from the
I think there's another actor dialect
that came after that plasma there's
ideas of combining the functional part
of Lisp with the object-oriented part of
something like small talk with logic
programming but the real kind of
breakthrough of how objects and
functions were related came when guy
Steele and Gerry Sussman were trying to
understand Carl Hewitt's actor language
so the actor language the message
passing system and so they figured they
could try to understand the concepts by
writing an interpreter for a dialect of
that which is very lispy so they
extended Mac Lisp to have a language
that they were trying to understand what
is message passing what is an object and
that language became known as scheme so
god known as scheme and what they did
was they wrote an interpreter like what
I just said earlier is a short program
and and they thought well in order to
capture some of the essence of what an
object is
what they want to do is is an object is
is really like a a function that has no
name perhaps and it gets as an argument
a message and that it looks at the
message and decides what to do okay but
in their interpreter they had a separate
branch for is this a function versus is
this an object I'm sending a message to
and so they wrote some different code
for each and then as they refactored the
code they didn't have that term back
then when they refactored the code they
noticed that these two versions of eval
were exactly the same actually apply
were exactly the same yeah
then they realized oh message passing is
a form of function calling or function
calling is a form of message passing and
objects are a form of function or
functions are a form of object and so
they made that conclusion but sadly or
happily I don't know people rapidly
forgot that because they thought scheme
was so cool
because it had these called lexical
closures so another concept in Lisp is
this first class Ness and so that means
that anything that exists in the
language can be returned as a value
passed as an argument stored in an array
so you can get two functions you can do
that two objects but soon thereafter a
lot of different experimentation wrong
with different types of object-oriented
extensions so there was loops there was
common loops there and I forget all
their names and some of them were
message passing and then someone came up
with the idea together with a couple of
ideas one was to if you have message
passing then you're sending a message to
one thing right so if you think about
Lisp you say well message passing is
like a function call so the object is
the function and I'm going to send it a
message and that message is one of the
arguments but you might send it some
other arguments so people started to
write methods basically and objects that
would sort of look at the first argument
at runtime and decide which method to
use that but when people looked at that
they saw that the the method called the
method
the message sends it's invoking the
method if it had more than one argument
it looked like you know send message to
foo ABCD night for four arguments they
said well you know Steele and Sussman
taught us that the send message doesn't
count so I can take the you know the
object food would make it the first
thing so isolate with a function yeah
then you've had ABCD and and the first
argument is treated especially why why
is the first argument special so they
started to think well maybe at runtime
you would look at all of the arguments
and you would invoke the method that was
most appropriate for all of them in the
example they used was suppose that
you're drawing something on a display
yeah so the classical way of doing that
is you send a message to what if the art
the object that says display yourself so
then that thing has to figure out what
about the display is it a piece of paper
is it a printer or is it a handheld
device that have them then they had
handled devices but they weren't
electronics like a spoon and stuff like
that
and so they said well it's kind of goofy
to ask an object to think about a
display even if they could do it very
abstractly since they would say all
right so I want to define a method that
when it's handed you know an object of
this class and it's you want to display
it on a display of this type then it
would just go right to the code right
that was called generic functions okay
and so a generic function is well and so
the arithmetic about the thick functions
in Lisp or like that so you can say plus
and an integer or an int and a real
number and it figures out what code to
run or do the conversion etcetera on its
own so they just generalize that so see
loss which became the dominant sort of
object or thing has that so it has multi
methods which are methods that are
defined and then because when you have
multiple objects that sort of
participate in selecting a method you
don't really associate the method with
one thing yeah there's no so much of
this thing there's no special this and
so what you do is you associated with
the generic funk
yeah which makes sense in some ways and
then ideas that came along at the same
time were multiple inheritance right and
so that that came from a guy named
Howard cannon and flavors which is he
sort of thought a little bit like
aspects are sort of thought of today but
you know there's some kind of
functionality that sort of the main
functionality but you want to add
something on you want to add a lock to
some some objects so that when you
operate on it you are lock it no one
else can operate your unlocking so he
invented these mix-ins
so that you could you know before you do
it you do the lock and when you're after
you do what you do the lock but hidden
watch that code to be sprinkled
throughout right so he defined these
things which are before and after
methods which are kind of what you see
it asked yeah so multiple inheritance
was used for doing these mix-ins so the
intention was you would have a main sort
of single inheritance hierarchy for your
main thing and then if you wanted to
have different mix-ins they would have
their own hierarchy so they they would
not be blended right to generalize it
they blended so they had multiple
inheritance made things complicated
yeah and they would and the mix-ins
typically had done this before and after
things that would kind of enhance the
primary structures right right there and
so the the terminology they used was
there was the primary method and then
there were before-and-after methods and
and again the list people like to
generalize they said well yeah that's
just one type of method combination
so-called method combination so you have
before methods that might apply after
methods that might apply where you might
have something that's interposed so if
you have a certain you know certain
argument certain object you're sending
the message to logically then you might
well say well in this case instead of
using the usual thing I'll do something
instead those round methods yeah so and
so that was called standard method
combination but you could have any kind
so what you could do is you could say
well if I invoke this you know generic
function what I want to do is is run all
of the methods that apply and they all
didn't it and we assumed that they were
her numbers will take the average or
will add the mob so you could define any
type of method combination that would
examine what methods were going to use
and what the classes were and it's all
part of the sort of meta circular type
reasoning very elegant very complicated
that led to this meta object protocol
thing which we probably would be a
separate episode right now it's so big
it's a big topic yeah you already
mentioned scheme yeah and in the term C
loss or clause is difficult what you
call it I call it C laws most people
gravitate to that these days but is also
okay the CL stands for common lisp all
right so can you briefly mention what
what's which significant dialects or
derivations of Lisp ixus scheme yeah so
the primary ones well the primary ones
these days essentially just Common Lisp
and scheme or the - yeah back in the 70s
and 80s because of the AI labs the
artificial intelligence labs were
separate there was only a rudimentary
internet at the time called the ARPANET
not everyone was on it that meant that
every lab developed their own dialect of
Lisp and so there was lore Lisbon
standard Lisp and MI necklace been
Stanford Lisp and UC Irvine Lisp go on
for hours of although just the names of
them Common Lisp was it an endeavor to
unify them so all of those AI ish type
of Lists became common lisp and so many
people liked scheme because it was small
and elegant and didn't it wasn't so
side-effect e yeah they went off on
their own so they developed different
dialects of scheme yeah so I think this
is this imperative stuff you talked
about before is something that is more
or less in common list but not in scheme
so you do have it they don't have it but
they don't it's just downplayed okay
they they try to write in a more
functional way Common Lisp so the manual
for Common Lisp is 600 pages the manual
for scheme scheme you just got a lot
bigger recently but up until one or two
years ago it was like 30 pages easier
and there were some other concepts in
scheme that caught on so I think I'll
continue
Asians alright yeah yeah I'm topic these
days in web development that's right
right so what a continuation is suppose
you're doing a computation and suppose
you're you're producing a list of things
or suppose you're doing a web
transaction yeah so you might want to
sort of return a value now but reserve
the right to sort of go back to where
you were right and so that's what a
continuation is a continuation is it's
something gets returned it's a function
and it says if you invoke that function
on an argument then you sort of return
to where that function where that
continuation was and you resume you kind
of saved the computation to somewhere
and go back there so cookies are sort of
a silly way of implementing continuation
so there are some web servers written in
scheme where continuations basically get
passed back and forth you know they they
they pass tokens instead to refer to the
continuation but the server will hold a
continuation etc comic seaside and small
talk that's the same writing yeah
exactly and so common lisp doesn't have
that's another big distinguishing
feature try out the macros are a little
bit different there's some technical
problems that I'm sure the listeners
don't want to hear about but if they
want to know what the heck I'm talking
about just Google for or AltaVista for
or Yahoo for or whatever hygienic macros
hygienic macros and that'll they'll tell
you more than you want to know I also
think that Lauren strat mentioned that
in the episode on compile time add a
program with converge he also has
something with her getting baptized yeah
ok let's get a bit more practical in a
way that we stop talking about concepts
and theory whereas Lisp used these days
and maybe if ever us inning I'd say why
isn't it used much these days what's the
state of Lisp today so this is used
because I would say sporadically it's
still used in a some but not a huge
amount of AI research there are some
commercial endeavors that are using Lisp
so for example what are they called
there's a company in Lexington
Massachusetts
they're called ITA so I don't know what
the ITA stands for apologize for that'
and dan Weinreb is one of the folks
there they are putting together and I
guess they have deployed an airline
reservation system common Lascaux so
there's a couple of companies like that
yahoo store sort of does this thing that
you know enables people to produce
stores storefronts yeah is written in
common lisp there's a you know some
specialized like some vision computer
vision stuff is writen in lists some
robotic stuff is written in Lisp and
it's just sporadically here and there
but commercially it's still viable
there's still some Lisp companies out
there that produce implementation but it
didn't catch on as a mainstream was it
maybe because it is too flexible too
powerful or is it because it doesn't
have curly braces as some folks say
there's a lot of reasons for that at
your listeners of a certain age will be
completely surprised to learn that in
the mid early to mid 1980s Lisp was the
java of its day okay that people the
investment and the business community
thought that artificial intelligence was
really going to take off with Appert
systems and all that yeah and so the
language of expert systems was Lisp and
AI was gonna take over the world
and so I believe there was a
Businessweek cover article about Lisp
and Forbes had articles about Lisp and
and I and others were you know on radio
programs and all sorts of stuff like you
know lists because they do come back
around and so two things happened are
two converging to things converged one
was what I call AI winter I can't
remember if I invented that term or
Earle such a dot II did it was during an
interview that he and I did kind of like
this one yeah
where's toward the end of 1980s the AI
companies were really good at hyping
what they could do and they weren't so
good at delivering result
business results so a lot of the company
said well it's because we're using Lisp
you know Lisp is not statically typed
and so it's a little bit big you know
it's a huge huge huge language you know
the runtime for common lisp is three
megabytes okay so your listeners should
be laughing now because what is the
average size of a you know Java program
these days a hundred and fifty billion
gigabytes or something
so three megabytes back ten was
considered out rate completely
outrageous because it didn't have static
typing static typing was optional in
Common Lisp that meant that the compiler
had to produce code that always checked
the types so would go a little slower so
it was slow
it was hard for beginners to write good
code and so you needed you know really
good wizard level variants of
programmers there weren't very many of
them so slow he was big complicated sort
of more oriented mathematicians and
practical people and all of that kind of
conspired to furless to roughly
disappear for most of the 1990s there
any Lisp hidden in any of today's
languages is there any Marathi successor
of Lisp maybe or what's going to happen
with Lisp in the future I think that you
can see the influences of Lisp in in
lots of places so Ruby certainly I think
owns meta programming right zealotes
yeah and any of the garbage-collected
languages list had a garbage collector
in 1958 1959 and had garbage collection
throughout and so obviouly
you know said oh of course small talk
will have garbage collection that's been
adopted by java and that's sort of a
major reason for its kind of success I
think for some types of programmers and
some applications yeah Lisp is used
sometimes an extension language it just
as a scripting language in some
situations I think in in Europe again
and you can talk to us people like
Pascal Costanza French like that is is
kidding
little bit of a resurgence starting to
be used for more exploratory stuff in
the Universities and some companies I
would like it to see a little bit of a
comeback because it's a very nice
language buzz from my point of view you
have to do a language research
experimentation absolutely yes and so
yeah I think it might have a little bit
of resurgence but I think it's most main
influence will be through the ideas that
spread all right let's talk a little bit
about you Oh recently mentioned moved
from from Santa IBM so what did you do
at Sun and why did you do did you go to
high payment what do to there yeah so
it's a little bit more of the story that
might be of some interest to listeners
mostly because it's uh it's a fun story
for me to tell and as I'd like to tell
it might sound interesting so in the
1995 for one reason or another I decided
to go back and get a degree in poetry
mm-hm
so that's when I went to park place
systems so I went to school in a low
residency MFA program and my company had
failed lucid it field in 1994 and so my
goal was my plan was I'd go back for a
couple of years get an MFA and then go
back to doing research language research
using less pot okay so I went off and
kind of didn't pay any attention to
computer science stuff for 1995 to 1998
when I came back basically all of my
research fields were deleted there was
no longer possible to do research
there's no place that I could do
research using Lisp there's no place I
could do research in Lisp on Lisp I
couldn't
there's no departments you know the
University departments that would hire
me there were no companies that did it
there were no conferences for it anymore
they all got taken over by the
functional programming guys there are no
journals that I could publish in and you
can imagine if you were a sort of an
academically minded person to go away
for a couple of years and have your
entire field deleted fascinating so it
was quite frustrating so at that point I
said okay well I'll just consider myself
a poet supporting myself by working in
the computer industry and
so bill joy called me up and he wanted
me to do some consulting for him and so
bill joy is one of the founders of Sun
right he had a lab in Aspen called Aspen
small works he had two projects he want
me to consult on one was supporting
Christopher Alexander implementing some
of his new ideas on what he calls the
nature of order so I served as advisor
to bill joy who was funding this and the
second one was to help with this project
that bill joy basically wanted to become
open-source mm-hm
so the Alexander thing kind of went away
quickly but then I started to work with
Bill and Sun on making this one project
open source and then once that had a
little the success that say getting that
project to be open source
he decided that Sun should move toward
open source so I spent
how long was I had Sun so from 1999
until this last February so that some
number of years I was mostly converting
the company to an open source company ok
so learning and teaching about licenses
teaching how to build communities they
are trying to figure out how companies
could participate in open source is
really not like what sort of open source
was about teaching management coming up
with business strategies eventually my
colleague I Ron Goldman wrote a book on
that which is kind of it's sort of like
a handbook for businesses on how to do
open source of what it all means but a
little link to it in the few notes and
so being an open source book it is
available online for free right but you
can also buy it so there's a there's a
but sure there's a PDF of it but
certainly a HTML version of it that's
easily available and I think open source
books have to be that way
and when we sort of succeeded when Ron
Goldman the co-author and I succeeded in
that we went back into son labs and to
work on some some research on keeping so
we call it self sustaining systems how
to
kind of marry traditional programming
with some biological concepts to sort of
keep programs alive to sort of solve
some problems on both sides of that
equation Sun labs is a very mmm
old-fashioned type of lab it's very
engineering oriented lab and they were
not as as friendly I would say toward a
project that was very expensive like
that yeah so it just felt a little bit
like that
madhu ngahiwi of this year I moved to
IBM research where I think there's a
little more freedom it's a little bit
bigger company there's a little bit more
resources they seemed to understand so I
was the general chair of uppsala they
mentioned 128 weeks so if you do the
math that's like more than two years
yeah it was full time so it was full
time for me for the last since June one
some walleye are certain by October
November five months of full time five
months of half-time to three-quarters
time and then the rest of the months
were about 25% times that's a big big
biggest yes absolutely oops law is
complex I'm have you been gathering
these interviews yeah and you're working
on this ultra large-scale system stuff
right so we've had an episode on that's
right so a couple years ago I joined
this task force it was looking at task
force sound like a really military thing
a study group for ultra large scale so
what would it mean to have the system of
a billion lines of code an example how
would you put that together and write
well would there be an architect could
there be that a single mind to conceived
of it so I work on that I work on some
of the self-sustaining system stuff and
so and I do some public services things
like oops long cool so to wrap this
thing up do you want to briefly talk a
little bit about your poetry side and
how you think poetry literature should
go or should be of more importance in
the software field and this kind of
stuff yeah there's a couple of aspects
of
when I went I didn't have a literature
background when I went back to school
and learning writing and and sort of
learning about creativity was not what I
expected and the thing they were
surprising about it
is that it can be taught more or less
yeah and it's taught by a way of
teaching and not by the the subject
matter are not content that sort of
thrown at you right and the way you
learn is it's sort of creating and
revising and examining other creations
while reflecting while thinking about it
while writing about what you're doing
and what you see and the other thing
that I found out was that creativity
comes from being having a sort of
diversity of ideas and my background
putting together you know synthesizing
things and I think all of that applies
to science that the methods of teaching
the way you teach writing that you teach
art should be used for teaching design
software design right and and stuff like
that so I've been working a little bit
on creating an MFA of softwares our MFA
of design for that also I think a lot of
the ways of doing exploration besides
total concept of getting lost in order
to discover I think applies to the work
we do is technologists engineers and and
I think it's it's quite informative yeah
writing poetry itself is quite an
interesting enterprise because you need
to open yourself up to a type of
observation that's that you can learn
how to do that is is not that commonly
used or not consciously used in the in
the software world of the computer
science world the way I sort of starting
to talk about it these days it's sort of
you know the influence of chaos on
reason so you know it's so going back
sort of an AI way of thinking about
things imagine he had it like a theorem
prover that was trying to reason about
chess or doing something like that
and running at the same time and same
address space was this sort of rapidly
associative program that's just sort of
every time the rational part was sort of
trying to prove something or looking at
a concept
then this other thing would shout out
anything that was related metaphorically
or sort of linked together
that's what creativity in the poetry
world feels like that there's this
chaotic thing that's going on that you
sometimes pay attention to and it just
didn't forms you so I'm trying to sort
of spread that idea and get other people
to work and think that way because I
think it would help them yeah so that's
that's the that's the thing the other
thing that's interesting about is for
the last seven years I've written a poem
a day I've seen that on your
website and so in the poetry world the
idea of writing a poem a day for a week
is more than most poets can bear writing
a poem a day for a month is considered
impossible there's one or two people who
have done it for a year and doing it for
seven years in a row what I've gotten to
a place in what it's like to write
poetry I'm not a great poet that the the
poet's that I know who are good poets
see you know when I talk about my
process now it's so different from what
they do that they want to understand
because no one go has gone that far with
it so I'll put a link to some of them
yeah so I think that there's you know I
think that scientists and artists need
to get together more mansoor help each
other out we're all interested in the
same things ultimately one last thing
that's worth mentioning is that I think
it was you who introduced the Writers
Workshop concept known from literature
into the patterns community right so
that's another kind of cross bleeding of
these difficult yeah okay thank you Nick
I think else you wanted to say before we
shut this down I really enjoy software
engineering radio as you know or your
your listeners know we used you for
doing some hard Kasper oops law thank
you haha just love the way you do this
so that is of course we're really good
to hear Thank You dick for these nice
words and thank you for the interview I
know you have been very busy at hoops
land you still found the time to talk to
us thank you very much before we shut
down this episode I want to play a song
it is called God wrote in Lisp it's
obviously about Lisp
I've gotten to know this song during
talk dick and guys deal gave hoopla it
was called fifty and fifty it was about
fifty different interesting features and
fifty programming languages over the
last years really really great talk
standing ovations at the end so the song
I'm gonna play is from the round bottom
album by Prometheus music and Elly
Goldberg from Prometheus music allowed
us to use it on the podcast it's
performed by Julia Eckler and the
lyricist is pop can f ski have fun
listening to it and talk to you at the
next AC radio podcast episode bye
[Music]
I was tore December
in my second year's school
it's kind of like construction work with
a tooth for a tooth
[Music]
so when I made my senior year
I threw my coat away and learn the way
to program but I
prefer to
[Music]
now some folks on the internet put their
faith in C++ they swear that it's so
it's what God used for us
and maybe it lets mortals dredge their
objects from the sea life
why only God
[Music]
three
god
when he
[Music]
recursive
and when
I
there's no flair
No
to
[Music]
with it
now I've used a son under Unix
so I've seen what see can hole I've
served four girls found what for Travis
for got bad job stuff down gold no the
chance thought I'd write COBOL code
snowball's chance in hell and I
basically Hey
so I won't use ap
[Music]
now God must know all these languages
and a few
[Music]
the Lord made sure when each sparrow
falls that its flesh will be reclaimed
and the Lord could not count grains of
sand with a 32-bit word who knows where
we would go to
if less burned what
great
[Music]
destroy form and Odyssey
Oh
[Music]
and blow
burn unbelievers do
stays too
so hero
Oh
[Music]
so he rolled it all
Oh
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se
- radio dotnet although we prefer
entries in our comment system on the
website so other people can see what you
think
Software Engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details